Hi, Vadim, nice to talk with you.
I’m teaching C and C++ in my university.
I took the source code in OpenCV as an example to the students.
And I also suggested my students to learn C++ from OpenCV.
I found the class cv::Mat is an excellent example.
And, I know you designed the class.
So
Could you tell me some history of the Mat class?
And why to design a new C++ class?
I remember at the beginning,
OpenCV used the IplImage and CvMat structure for images.
So, why you designed it?
Can you introduce a little bit to us?
Yes, sure.
I'd like to talk to you again, Shiqi.
First of all, I'm very pleased that, OpenCV is now taught in universities including your university,
and you chose CV::Mat as am example of C++ design.
Actually it's a big pleasure for me and for the whole OpenCV team that
our pieces of OpenCV design are used in such a way.
Indeed, it took several years for OpenCV team to come up with this C++ class.
In the very beginning,
the very first structure in OpenCV
as you correctly pointed out was IplImage.
This is because OpenCV was started at Intel in 1998
as a close source library, and then released as open source.
At that time, at Intel, the family of performance libraries,
like for signal processing acceleration, for image processing acceleration,
and like one of the libraries was IPL,
Image Processing Library by Intel.
And it uses IplImage as the main data structure.
The original OpenCV was planned as addition to IPL
or IPL concentrates on image processing,
and OpenCV will concentrate on computer vision.
In the begin, OpenCV was called CVL,
Computer Vision Library.
So it even use the same name pattern as IPL.
just a set of computer algorithms of image processing, computer vision.
Soon, we realized the IplImage was not enough,
because in computer vision, if you do, for example,
camera preparations, some 3D vision, whatever you need, general matrix class.
And sometimes, for example,
you need more than two dimensional arrays,
like 3 dimensional arrays.
Sometimes you need sparse multi-dimensional arrays.
So in addition to IplImage,
we also create CvMat, CvMatND indeed and CvSparseMat
to like other those use cases.
Then a time later, Intel abandoned IPL in favor of like library of low level primitives.
It is called IPP and it is still used in OpenCV for acceleration.
We have to maintain compatibility with IPL since then.
Because like uh, the library was gone and replaced with IPP.
So we mostly used CvMat C structure for most of use cases
for point clouds, for mathesis, for images.
But we constantly got requests from users
to introduce C++ API
because C++ was much more convenient to use, instead of C.
In the year 2008, when Willow Garage company started to found OpenCV,
by the way Willow Garage company also created ROS, Robot Operating System
It was a quite big startup at a certain point.
It founded OpenCV development.
They gave us resources and we started to think
how to redesign OpenCV to use C++ API.
and definitely we need C++ data structure.
instead of CvMat and IplImage C structures.
So we looked around,
and for the source of inspiration,
and we found that Matlab is a very good example of good design.
That is Matlab is not an as flexible language as C or C++.
But it is super convenient.
It has this matrix, or array data type. And all the toolboxes in Matlab, use this data type.
Therefore, there is no absolutely not compatibility issues
If you want to use those toolboxes.
You just download them and use together
without any convert stage, structures from one type to another.
You just use those toolboxes together.
And they, MathWorks, even use those arrayed data types for images.
In matlab, there is image processing toolbox,
and it also uses matrix data type.
I really like this idea that
one data type is used for any kind of array.
So we just tried to replicate Matlab API
as goal as we could.
we wanted convenient element access operations, etc.
we wanted like convenient element, //TODO access separations, etc.
So we created this class, C++ structure, cv::Mat.
They replaced all of the structures,
IplImage, CvMat, CvMatND
Sparse model was a seperate structure
But all the dense arrays were replaced with just a single structure.
We know different Mat objects may share the same memory for matrix data to avoid memory leak.
There is a complex mechanism in Mat class.
If you redesign Mat class now, will you use smart pointers in the new C++ standards?
We did have a shared pointer
appeared in C++11 if I'm not mistaken.
In C++20,
it was special version of this shared pointer that can use atomic operations.
And we create cv::Mat in 2009,
so even 2 years before C++11,
so we couldn't wait for the new C++ standard to come out.
So we used our own implementation of shared pointer.
Of course it's not a new idea.
It was well known for decades.
Even Python created in 90s.
It used shared pointers with a reference counter to manage memory.
And it still uses this technique.
So we wanted memory to be managed automatically.
And we want memory to be managed in the thread safe manner.
So we wanted to use atomic operations from the very beginning.
We implemented this mechanism in cv::Mat.
And I would say that overall cv::Mat implementation
and architecture are quite complex.
If you look inside, you would notice that
for example, there is not a signal reference counter but instead there are two reference counters in each matrix.
So overall,
I would say,
if we use this modern C++ standard to implement
those reference counting, shared memory,
I would say overall implementation would not become noticeable simple
In another words,
if we create cv::Mat now
I would say the implementation will be almost the same as it was like many years ago.
Even though, C++ standard going in the right direction.
For CV Ptr class [TODO:vp] OpenCV, we used shared pointer for matrix
I would say we would use the same implementation as before.
Mat class is not a template class.
In my class,
I ask my student to implement a matrix class
to improve their programming skills.
I asked them that the matrix class they designed should support many different data types,
including 8-bit integers, 16-bit integers and floating point, like that.
Most student used class template.
So I think it's a very straightforward idea to use a template for that.
Could you tell us why the Mat class you designed
is not a template class?
In OpenCV team, we had some discussions like how to implement the thing
and at some point, at Intel, we had another project that implemented biasing networks [TODO:VP biasing?]
That was quite complex library
they chose to go completely into that way.
So they created everything in templates.
And I know that currently you heavy use of template is one of the trends in C++.
Many people prefer to use templates.
to get the best efficiency.
In our case, we deliberately chose not to go completely to that way
Because we saw bad example, a library becomes unusable
because of its completely template
so we can take very long time to compile code that uses those libraries.
So when we speak about like generic library of algorithms
STL library with containers, basic algorithms like sort()
It's not that much complex, but there is still some, but it's not that much. In the case of computer vision.
Algorithms are quite, may become quite complex
And so if you make a matrix class as template,
It is a strong motivation to put a lot of code into header files
to make everything templates.
And for developers, it may become a simpler solution.
But for users, normally most of OpenCV users they use just a tiny part of OpenCV
But for them, to wait those long minutes or even hours for their code to be compiled
it is a big problem.
Unfortunately, together with templates and C++, they didn't introduce modules.
Modules are common to C++ only now,
and even now, the support for modules is immature.
Maybe several years later, when modules become widespread,
when compiling complete code becomes much more efficient,
then maybe more libraries will come out and will use template.
Now, it's like not a good idea.
So the first reason is we want to avoid long compile time.
The second reason is Python.
So even 10 years ago, we understood Python has a good, has a great potential. It is an excellent language.
Besides that has been Java that we also wanted to support
and also languages like Java has some support for templates.
But it's not completely compatible with C++.
Python, it doesn't have any template.
And we wanted OpenCV supported by Python [TODO:VP] as well.
So if you have template library,
creating code for Python is quite complex tasks.
Basically you need to implement [TODO:VP] all those functions in Python wrapper.
and see what is the actual data type that the user called or particular instance of template implementation.
So it is not quite convenient.
So I think we did it the right way
and we make right decision not to implement multiple OpenCV templates [TODO:VP].
OK, thank you.
Yeah, I also learned a lot from it.
Because we always balance between many factors.
So you introduced the factors in designing OpenCV,
but I also found there is a class template which is very similar to Mat in OpenCV, its name is Mat_.
Since we have Mat class, why to design Mat_, the template.
You just explain the template maybe have some shortcomings,
but we find there's a template for Mat.
Yes, yes.
Indeed there's another class that is
has this underline in the end of the name
and it doesn't introducing new members.
So it's finally compatible with normal cv::Mat in both ways.
So if we use, and it derives from Mat,
you can basically use it instead of Mat.
The only reason was to provide convenient element access operations.
If you have, for example,
some matrix algorithm that appears [TODO:VP] floats
First option to access the elment, you use to play at<>() method
with angle brackets<>, you just say that
myMatrix.add(10, 20), in angle brackets<>,
you put data type like float, then you put indices in the parenthesis.
And with Mat_, you just use parentheses myMatrix(10,20)
You don't need add<>() with angle brackets. So it's another notation.
But I would say that the number of algorithms that access elements directly in this way [not many].
Some, savings that you type less symbols
it is so small, I could say that if we design matrix class today again,
I would not create this extra template class
because most people just use normal cv::Mat.
Yeah, yeah.
OK, I have another question.
The question, it's about hardware, because currently there are many kinds of hardware than in the past
in the past, maybe only CPU? Or mostly CPU. Currently we have GPU, NPU or VPU
Most of them have separate memory,
Is it possible to design an universal Mat class which can handle different kind of memory?
So, indeed nowadays
Using GPU, or specialized accelerators to speed up computer vision is a very popular trend.
Everybody goes in this direction,
For example, Nvidia Xavier used in cars, it's indeed very popular.
Unfortunately, from software site, there is no good standard
to program those hardware in an universal way.
About 10 years ago, when we had a project with AMD and Intel,
to bring OpenCL support into OpenCV,
I thought that OpenCL would soon become such a new universal standard.
that everybody would use OpenCL to program that hardware.
Hardware like GPU or specialized computer vision accelerators.
So, for OpenCL in OpenCV we created special class called cv::UMat that people can use to access OpenCL functionality.
And also OpenCV included several hundreds of OpenCL kernels to accelerate various algorithms from image processing to machine learning and so on.
Unfortunately, now OpenCL is sort of semi-abandoned standard.
It's still in the development, but it looks most manufacturers try to use something else.
Like Apple uses Metal standard, then on Android, Vulkan is more popular for game, for example.
Also there are some immature standards, for example,
the standard called OACC (OpenACC), open accelerator.
It aims at to bring some extensions to C++ standard to upload some loops to GPU.
But it is not quite mature, so I would say we're still waiting for such a standard come out to conveniently program various hardware.
Currently there are some positive trends for example,
like Vulkan group in Khronos community and OpenCL group, they work together
to provide OpenCL compatibility for Vulkan based hardware and such.
So maybe OpenCL is not completely dead and it will maybe revised at some point.
Yes, we are still waiting.
Without the standard it is difficult to come up with such a universal class
because you do not know which should be added, because everybody uses the different API.
I still have another question.
Actually it's two questions.
The first question is does OpenCV have any plan to update Mat class to a newer one?
Or we will continue to use the current one?
Yes, so OpenCV is quite large library with many users,
and so there are no plans to completely replace the cv::Mat with something else.
And cv::Mat is quite flexible for example
for Python bindings, users do not see this cv::Mat class.
They operate on common ...
on very popular in Python world, NumPy arrays.
And internally, those Python arrays are converted to cv::Mat, usually it happens without copying any data.
So it's very efficient.
We try to use this zero copy techniques.
Internally, as I said, we do not plan to completely replace cv::Mat with something completely new.
But we want to make some upgrades to cv::Mat.
First of all, we plan to extend the number of data types supported.
So maybe it will be some new integer data types, also we plan to add BFloat16.
Brain Floating 16, it's the relatively new 16 point format developed by Google.
and use in their TPU accelerators, and also it is now supported by Intel hardware
Upcoming ARM v9 and some other architectures.
So it's quite popular and we want to add support for it.
Another new feature is
to support one dimensional arrays.
As I said, we borrowed this cv::Mat class idea from Matlab,
and in Matlab, there is no one dimensional array, as far as I know.
One dimensional array is represented as two dimensional 1xN and Nx1 array.
And in OpenCV we took the same convention, but it appears to be not quite convenient for Python bindings
and for some deep learning areas that
we are trying to add to OpenCV currently like speech recognition
or whatever some areas on dimensional arrays are important
We want to support for real one dimensional arrays to OpenCV.
The third feature, we are still thinking of it.
But, maybe we will add some tag into cv::Mat that will indicate, that will provide some indication to what is the data, that marks the source.
For example, the tag can be RGB or BGR to indicate what is the order of channels.
Maybe it will solve some old problems, when people just put,
use some matrix with incorrect data channels, and sometimes they get wrong visualization.
Instead of a red face, you will get blue faces. In some cases,
You just get maybe slightly worse performance from some deep nets, object detection networks.
so it still detects objects, but not as good as with proper order channels.
So it's a very subtle bug to detect.
And maybe with this tags, this problem will disappear.
So we are still thinking of..
Yeah, sure, yeah because in my course, the final project is to do some CNN
They should implement CNN by themselves.
So in the data reading from the image, the default channel is BGR, a lot of students were confused by that and made some errors.
I know there will be some students from my class and also from maybe all over the world will watch this video.
Do you have any suggestions for the students in computer science, especially the students who are learning C++
Yeah, so
I think that currently there are many sources of information,
there are many good online courses on computer vision.
I'm glad that you are teaching the C++ class, I saw some bits of it and I think it's very professional.
I'm sure that students will learn a lot from it.
So maybe I have just a few common words,
feel free to ignore them completely, just from my experience of developing software quite a few years.
I would suggest students to pay more attention to algorithms, concepts, technologies,
rather than particular features, particular programming language.
Many years ago, Fortran was the most language for computing,
then C became the dominant language, then C++.
I would say currently maybe Python is used more especially with special acceleration extensions, like NumPy [TODO:VP] whatever or Siphon[TODO:VP].
Maybe Python is used more actively for computing than everything else.
So do not pay too much attention to the particular feature, particular language,
and do not try to use all those fancy features of the language that you just learned in your project
Because those features just exist and you want to make your code look cool by using all those features
because this's a good change that a couple of months later you won't be able to read your own code because it's too complex.
I think this suggestion is especially for C++, right?
Because there are too many features in C++.
Yes, C++, I would say, in the recent standards, they made some small convenient to you like modules.
It's important feature I believe.
But on the other hands, languages becoming quite more and more complex.
And so you need to develop proper style of using C++, not to shoot yourself on the foot.
And try not to use manual memory allocation,
To use exisiting containers like std::vector, or if you use OpenCV, use cv::Mat, etc.
Like try to put some regression test before you do any refactoring or optimization.
There should be some tests, of course.
As I said, develop some methodology, a proper methodology how to
create robust software that is easy to debug or doesn't need to be debugged at all, it works out of the box.
Instead of just using very complex language constructions that you may not fully understand.
Yeah, sure. I also found a lot of students, they spend a lot of time on debugging.
It takes them a lot of time to find a very tiny bug, it's very difficult in C and C++,
because there are memory leaks and maybe some pointers have invalid values,
it's quite common, yeah.
Yes, so like automatic class you mentioned, for example, shared pointers, it is another very good tool
when people avoid using raw pointers in C++.
But instead use containers like cv::Vec or cv::Mat or shared pointers.
The number of memory leaks problems go almost to zero.
Yeah, thank you, thank you for the suggestions!
Yeah, you are welcome!
I believe the students will be benefited from your suggestions and also your introduction to OpenCV, thank you!
You are welcome!